I don't know about you, but I am
allergic to my mouse. Every time I need
to lift my hand up off the keyboard and
click and drag, I feel like I'm slamming
on the brakes. As I'm used to cruising
through my codebase with speed and
precision. As a professional who's using
cursor every day to build software, I'm
obsessed with keyboard shortcuts. So, in
this video, I'll show you some of my
favorite cursor keyboard shortcuts and a
few interface tweaks that I've used to
really streamline my workflow because
that's what we do as professionals. We
master our tools and our flow. It's
about building speed and muscle memory
so that nothing gets in the way of our
creativity. You know, I've been playing
guitar my whole life. And once you've
been playing a while, you stop thinking
about scales and chords. Your hands and
your fingers, they just know where to go
so that you can focus on the music.
That's how I want coding to feel. When I
come in here and sit at my desk and fire
up cursor and claw code, I want to fly
through my codebase. I want to fire off
commands to my AI agent with just a few
keystrokes. I don't want to be thinking
about navigating anything. I want to
focus on building. So, if you're like me
and you want to stay sharp with your
craft and you want to stay ahead of the
curve when it comes to building with AI,
then I'd love for you to join my builder
briefing. It's a free 5-minute read that
I send out weekly to professional
builders like us. You can get on that by
going to buildermethods.com
and subscribers will be the first to
know about my cursor course coming this
year. So, I'm going to cover several
areas where I spend a lot of time
working in cursor and I'll share all the
little keyboard shortcuts that I use in
all these different places. So, we're
going to start out with the workspace
and how I sort of manage that with the
keyboard. Then, of course, we're going
to look at how I interact with AI in
cursor with the uh the chat window and
working with AI in the files themselves.
Then I'll get into, you know, managing
your files explorer and, you know, going
through files and firing up new files
and things like that. Then we'll get
into working in the code themselves and
manipulating lines of code and jumping
around the codebase. And last but not
least is the terminal, of course, you
know, firing up new terminal tabs and
tabbing between them and all that kind
of stuff. Now, before I share my
shortcuts for everything, it's really
important for you to get into the habit
of customizing your keyboard shortcuts
for the moves that you make most often
throughout every day in cursor or in any
application that you use, right? It's
about building up that speed and muscle
memory for the most frequent actions.
So, in cursor, you can customize your
keyboard shortcuts in two ways. So, I'm
going to do commandshiftp. And by the
way, I am on a Mac, so you're going to
hear me say command a lot. I think the
alternative is control on Windows. So,
command shiftp will open up this options
picker. I don't know what they call
that. And you can just type in keyboard.
And there are these two options, right?
One is to go to your keyboard shortcuts
preferences. And that's that's like a
menu and an interface that you can use
to find um any keyboard shortcut and
customize it. You can search by the name
of the feature, which sometimes I just
don't know what features are called, but
you can also click this button and
search by the keyboard shortcut that you
already have. And then, of course, you
can go in here and customize them.
System means that it's like built into
the system, sort of like by default, and
user means that you have customized it.
Now, that's one way to customize your
shortcuts, but I actually prefer um
going into the JSON. This is like a code
version of the same thing or and
actually this lives in my user key
bindings JSON which means that this file
will override the the default key
bindings that ship with cursor. And also
keep in mind that cursor is a fork of VS
Code. So all of these features and
customization options and a lot of the
default key bindings come from VS Code.
And that might be helpful if you're ever
going into chat GPT or Claude or the AI
and cursor to ask for help with
keybindings. Even though they are aware
of cursor as a thing, it's sometimes
better to say, "Hey, in VS Code, how do
I change this or that?" When really
you're working in cursor because it is a
fork of VS Code. Anyway, this is my
personal uh key bindings JSON. This is
where I added um you know, a couple of
custom key bindings. There's actually
not a whole lot here. U I used to have
more, but I sort of like culled it down
to just the ones that I happen to
actually use all the time every single
day. I'm going to cover these
individually as we get through the
video, but I just wanted to point out
that here in the the JSON, you know, you
can give it a uh the the key command and
then this is the actual feature or
functionality in cursor or in VS Code
that you'll need to have exactly right.
It's often really hard to know exactly
what these things are called. you know,
you can sort of get a clue by by looking
through these keyboard shortcuts. That
is where I find that like asking chatgbt
or claude for um you know, what's the
name of this or that feature so that you
can target it in this user key bindings
file. The when setting means that um you
know this key command will only be
effective when you're uh in this
particular mode or state within a
cursor. And so since these are sometimes
kind of cryptic to read, I like to add
these comments to just remind myself
like what is each thing. All right, so
let's start at the workspace layout
level. This is what I'm looking at. I've
got my files on the left. I've got the
AI chat on the right. I've got my
terminal on the bottom and my file in
the middle. And I'm always toggling each
of these panels on and off. So popping
the terminal up and down for me, that's
command T. And I think that that is a
customization that I made. Yeah, toggle
terminal. Command T. That's this
workbench action terminal. Toggle
terminal. And then my files explorer on
the left. I can toggle that open and
closed with commandB. And the AI chat on
the right. That is command L. I'd say
most of the time I'm in this layout with
my files shown on the left and the AI
chat on the right. Even if I'm not
actively using the chat, I sort of like
to have this, you know, narrowish
uh view of my file right in the center
of my screen. I find that when I close
out the file explorer, you know, my head
is turning too much to the left to see
my code. So, um, you know, I like to
keep it right in the center of the
screen because I have like neck and back
issues.
You know, back in the VS Code days
before cursor came around, I had it
flipped. I had my files on the right.
And if I open up my uh user settings,
that was this one. I I ended up
commenting this out. So, it used to be
like that for me where I had, you know,
just my my files on the right, which was
sort of nice because my code didn't
really change its position, but then
once the uh once the AI chat came into
play with cursor, um it sort of made
more sense to put that on the right
side. So, I'm going to comment that out
again. And the other sort of workspace
view that I use from time to time is the
new background agents feature in cursor.
You can get to that with command E. And
that's where I can fire up a new
background agent and then u when I have
them running it it can open up a a
larger interface to see my background
agents. I have an entire video on my
channel that dives into the background
agents feature in cursor if you want to
check that out. All right. So if you're
using cursor then of course you're
building with AI. So, let's dive into
the AI features in cursor and how I have
customized some of the shortcuts to fit
my workflow. Let's start with tab
completion. This is one of those things
that I think a lot of us developers have
like a lovehate relationship with. So,
I'll be on this line of code and I'll
hit return. And then, you know, it's
suggesting some new code for me to add,
which of course I can add with just a
tab. But, you know what? If I just want
to use the tab key like a normal tab key
and and add some space, you can't really
do that right out of the box. So I added
a shortcut for that. I can do control
tab to do a regular tab and then of
course shift tab to go back. That way I
can still use the tab completion which I
do a lot but whenever I need to do an
actual tab I'll just do you know control
tab like that. It's just part of my
muscle memory now even to the point
where if I'm in like a Google doc or
something and I want to tab I'm hitting
like control tab when really over there
I just need to use tab. And by the way,
my custom key binding for the uh control
tab shortcut is right here. So I've got
control tab as the key. The command is
tab and then I have when set to editor
text focus and not editor readonly and
not editor tab moves focus. This is the
line right there that allows me to set
up normal tabs. And while we're on the
subject of tab completions, you know,
the more that you use them, the more you
get a feel for how they actually work.
You know, I like to sort of tip off
cursor to sort of nudge it in the
direction that I want it to handle my
tab completion. It's kind of hard to
explain, but you start to notice that
like if you make one change, you'll
expect the tab completion to do the
rest. So, one example would be when I'm
working with Tailwind CSS. In Talwin 4,
we put configurations in CSS files. And
so this is usually how I handle um
setting up like my brand colors, right?
Where I have a primary color, a
secondary color, sometimes a tertiary, a
gray, and uh you know what? If I wanted
to like add another one um I don't know,
we'll call this like my active color,
right? So I want each of these lines to
be color active 50, active 100, active
200, right? So if I just change the
first one, and yeah, right away it's
it's starting to to see what I want. And
so it's like I I knew that was coming
because I sort of tipped it off by, you
know, putting my my down arrow on the
line below. It's it's sort of a feel
thing, you know. I just like this idea
of like playing the code and the
keyboard like an instrument and tab
completions is sort of like a big part
of that. Now, now one of the AI features
in cursor that for whatever reason I
just never really use, that's the inline
AI chat thing. I don't even know what
they call that. When you're in a file
like this, you can do command K and that
and that'll bring that up. I just never
touch that. I always use the chat window
on the side, which again I open up with
command L. And what I like about that is
I can highlight specific lines of code,
you know, and I would usually do
something like this and then command L.
And then I can see there that it it got
lines 25 through 28 into the context
window and it highlighted the chat
window. So, I can say, you know, explain
this and have it explain what's going on
there. Right. So, now that we're in the
chat window, which is where I spend a
lot of time in cursor, um, of course, we
can, uh, start up a new chat with
command N. Um, that's always good to
sort of like clear out the context and
just start over. That can help with
accuracy. And, you know, you'll need to
do that when your context windows just
go really long. And if you're moving on
to a new topic or a new question, it's
always good to sort of clear out any
past discussions that could throw AI off
a little bit. Now, in the chat window
itself, you can use the slash key to get
into some uh commands here. Like I just
did, reset the context, although um you
know, I usually just do that with
command N. Uh you can generate cursor
rules, but I usually do that manually.
So, I actually don't use these too much.
I just want to mention that you do have
a slash key that can get you into things
like that. Um, but one thing that I do
use quite a bit from the keyboard is
option command P. And that's going to
add specific files into my context. This
is what I do a whole lot. If I'm like in
this file here, but I know that I want
to ask a question that is going to
relate to something else. I could use
the mouse to click this tiny button over
here, but I want to stay away from my
mouse. So, I'm going to do option
command P. And then I can, you know, add
uh that that color CSS or I can uh find,
you know, application controller and add
that in there, right? And then I can
escape and I can ask a question. I don't
know what I would be asking with those
three files, but that's just an example.
All right, so now let's just have the AI
add a posts model to my application so
that I have uh some files that I can
accept.
By the way, Cursor just launched this
new feature called to-do lists, which is
pretty cool. it'll actually make a
little to-do list for itself and it'll
sort of track its progress throughout a
task like this. So, that's pretty cool.
Okay, so that is all done. And you know,
I've done a few videos on Claude code
and cursor and the differences between
them. And I must say that this part of
the workflow where I'm reviewing code
and I'm accepting individual changes,
this is really where cursor shines over
cloud code. As much as I love cloud code
and it's really capable as an autonomous
agent, cursor is really excellent for
going through, you know, multiple files
and changes. And so, one thing that I
can do here is I could click these
arrows to go through 10 different files
where it made some changes. But I can
also do option L and option H. That's
going to sort of page through uh these
10 different files and I can go into
each one and uh and take a look. I can
accept the individual file with command
return
and then I can sort of keep going
through command L, command H to go back
and forth. I can reject or accept
individual lines with command N, command
Y. But if I'm happy with all the files
and I want to accept them all in one
shot, then I can focus the chat window
here and I can do accept all. Instead of
doing that with my mouse, I'll do it
with my keyboard, which is command
return.
All right. So now let's turn our focus
over to the other side of my screen and
cursor and that's the file explorer
window. As I said earlier, I can toggle
it open and closed with commandB. And if
I have the file explorer already open,
but the file that I'm working in is
currently focused to shift the focus
over to the file explorer so that I can
move around and do things. I'll do
command shift E. So now the focus is on
my file explorer. And let's say I want
to um kind of collapse all these
different folders and subfolders, which
I have to do all the time. I'll do
control shift up just like that.
Everything becomes collapsed. And then I
often use the arrow keys to go to go up
and down or sometimes I'll just press
like P or the letter of of whatever it
is that I want to jump to here. And then
I'll hit the right arrow to open a
folder and I'll go down um left arrow to
close it. So I do that a lot. But really
the more professional way to jump around
your files of course is to hit command P
and search for any file that you want.
Right? So if I want to find the
application layout, I'll just go like
that. So command P all day long. That's
this might be my most used shortcut in
cursor. It opens up my recent files. And
one thing that you'll probably notice is
I don't have the file tabs across the
top. That's something that, you know,
usually comes with VS Code. I disabled
that feature because I hate to see all
those different tabs. There's it just
visually there's a lot of clutter. It
they're just not easy to navigate. So I
just use command P to jump around to my
recent files. Right? So if I'm in post,
I can go back to form. I can go back to
location. I could use control W to to
clear this out, I think. But I actually
almost never do that as you can see.
Okay. So it gives me this alert to do
it. I just never even use that shortcut.
I just always have, you know, my my
recent files um in this selector and
that's how I do it. And if I need to get
to a new file, again, I'll use the same
thing. CommandP, you know, and it'll get
me to where I'm going. That setting to
disable the tabs in cursor is um a user
setting, which again I did command
shiftp to open up um this like settings
navigator in cursor and I'll open up
user settings JSON
and this is the line. So, if I comment
this out and save my tabs come back, I
got to get those out of here. So, I'm
going to uncomment that and save. Okay,
as you can see, I uh I I I disable a lot
of the noise um that that comes with
cursor. I got a lot of these tips from
uh Caleb Porzio from LiveWire. And uh
you know, I won't go through all of
these here today, but this is a really
big one for me. uh disabling the tabs
which is workbench editor show tabs uh
single I guess I'm just showing a single
tab all the time and again I just use
the u this I don't know what you call
this like the file jumper thing sort of
jump around my files and then escape and
then I'm back in all right the last
thing that is files related of course is
creating a new file which I do all the
time for this I'm actually using an
extension so I'm going to open up my
extensions window which I can do
commandshiftx to get to those and I have
advanced new file. So what this does is
it gives me a shortcut. It's option
command N. And then here I can do all
sorts of things, right? Like I can I can
just start in the in the root and do
like custom folder,
custom file,
something like that. And just create a
new folder and a file all in one shot.
That's really easy. A lot easier than
doing like a a new file the the default
way. I really like that. All right. Now,
let's get our hands dirty in the code
itself. I know we don't do this a whole
lot anymore since AI is writing a lot of
our code, but I'm still in here fiddling
with lines of code pretty often. So, so
here are sort of like my code line
manipulation keyboard shortcuts, right?
One that I use all the time is
duplicating a line. So, if I want this
line to be duplicated, as long as my
cursor is anywhere on this line, could
be at the the beginning, the middle, the
end, I can just do command D and that
entire line will be duplicated. And that
duplicate line is in my key bindings.
That's right here. So, command D, editor
action, copy lines, down action when the
editor is in focus. Okay. Another one
that I use all the time is deleting an
entire line. So, let's say I want to
knock this whole line out. Again, my
cursor can be anywhere on this line. I'm
going to do command X to just knock out
the entire line. I'll undo that. And
that key binding is right here. Delete
line. Command X. We're going to delete
lines. All right. Another thing that
you'll do quite often is commenting out
lines. So again, my cursor can be
anywhere on a line and I can do commands
slash to comment out that line. Or I can
even highlight multiple lines and do
commands slash to comment all of them
out. And I can do the same thing to
uncomment. That one I'm using all the
time. All right. Folding code is also
something that I do quite often,
especially when I have a really long
file. So, you know, here's a here's a
method that I want to fold up. I'll do
commandshift open bracket to fold it up
and command shift closed bracket to open
it up again. Another one is moving a
line up or down. Right? So, again, I'll
just put the cursor anywhere on this
line. And if I want to move that up or
down, I'll do option down or option up.
Option down. I can move it anywhere I
want to. Option up. And I often combine
those with the folding. So, if I fold up
this uh method and highlight it, then I
can move that whole method up or down,
even though it's a really long piece of
code. So, I do that a lot as well. All
right. So, you've already seen me do
this a few times here, but so I'm
always, you know, looking to to jump the
cursor around. To jump to the end of a
line, I'll do command arrow right to
jump to the beginning of the line.
Command arrow left. To jump across every
word in a line, I'm holding down option
and right and left. That's a fast way to
get through it. And then selecting
lines. So let's say my cursor is like in
the middle of a line right here and I
want to select just the rest of the
line. I'll do command shift to the
right. So that's going to highlight
everything to the right of the cursor up
until the end of the line. The opposite
will be everything to to the beginning
of the line. Command shift left. Goes
like that. Um or I can go to the
beginning of the line and command shift
right to uh highlight the entire line.
So, let's catch up on some of these uh
customizations that I made in the
keybindings JSON. So, here is my fold
and unfold. That's shift command, open
bracket, and close bracket. That's
editor fold and editor unfold. Uh I have
duplicate line. And then I have uh
delete line. Um this was that uh normal
tab thing that I showed you earlier. The
last thing that I do quite often is just
jump the cursor to the very top or the
very bottom of a file. And that's just
command up to go to the very top,
command down to go to the very bottom.
Sometimes I do that to the to then do
command A to select everything. But
yeah, that's uh that's a handy one as
well. All right, let's talk about the
terminal. I'm spending more time than
ever in here, mostly because of cloud
code. And you know, if you've seen my
other videos on the channel about cloud
code, you know that of course you can
integrate cla code directly into cursor
as I've done. You know, I can do that
and pull up cloud code up here. But as I
talked about my workspace earlier, I
just don't like the placement of this in
the workspace. And so, uh, I really
don't use the builtin cloud code window.
Instead, I just prefer cloud code right
in the terminal, which is right here.
So, I open up my terminal, uh, with
command T. I toggle that up and down all
day long. Um, and so here in the first
terminal, I have Claude opened, and then
I opened up a second terminal. So to
open up a new terminal tab. So to open
up a new terminal tab, I'll do control
shift open bracket just like that. And
then to flip between my different
terminal tabs, I'm doing command shift
bracket left and bracket right. Just
like that. And to show you those custom
key bindings, we are toggling the the
terminal open and closed with command t.
This is the new terminal tab. Uh command
shift open bracket. navigating between
them, I think, is just a system built-in
uh keyboard shortcut for cursor. And
then, of course, uh clearing the
terminals. You know, if I have some
stuff here and I want to just get rid of
that, command K will clear it out for
me, which I do a lot. And in case you
didn't know, you can highlight stuff in
the terminal and then do command L to
take what's in the terminal, throw it up
into the AI chat. As I can see here, I
have lines 1 through 14 highlighted. So
then I can ask AI what's going on with
this error message that I'm seeing over
here. And a lot of times if I have like
really long logs, I'll need to just
highlight specific lines and then add to
chat with command L. You know, just like
that. Now, if you're a power user in
Cursor, and I'm going to say that you
are because you're watching this video,
getting those keyboard shortcuts down,
building that muscle memory, then you
may have heard about background agents
in Cursor. It's a newer feature. They
just made it even better in cursor 1.0.
And so I have a deep dive video going
into how you can use background agents
and cursor to crush your backlog. So,
right after you hit subscribe on this
channel, head over there and let's keep